export const BIOLOGYA2021 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Which of the following organelles is common to both plant and animal cells?",
A: "cellulose cell wall",
B: "chlorophyll",
C: "cell membrane",
D: "large vacuole",
answer: "C. Cell membrane",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. The section X and Y respectively are _________.",
A: "longitudinal and transverse",
B: "transverse and longitudinal",
C: "cross and transverse",
D: "transverse and cross",
answer: "B. transverse and longitudinal",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. The fruit that has the illustrated sections is a _________.",
A: "hesperidium",
B: "capsule",
C: "drupe",
D: "cypsela",
answer: "A. hesperidium",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The structure labeled I is associated with _________.",
A: "sexual reproduction",
B: "asexual reproduction",
C: "bud formation",
D: "gamete formation",
answer: "B. asexual reproduction",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The structure labeled (II) is the _________.",
A: "spore",
B: "stolon",
C: "columella",
D: "sporangium",
answer: "C. columella",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Which of the following statements about the structure labeled III is correct? It __________.",
A: "secretes digestive enzymes into the substrate",
B: "absorbs mineral salts from the soil",
C: "forms the root hairs of the organism",
D: "develops into stolon",
answer: "B. absorbs mineral salts from the soil",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The level of organization of the organism is ____________.",
A: "tissue",
B: "cell",
C: "organ",
D: "system",
answer: "B. cell",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. The organism belongs to the Phylum",
A: "Rhizopoda",
B: "Ciliophora",
C: "Euglenophyta",
D: "Rhodophyta",
answer: "C. Euglenophyta",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. A plant cell placed in a solution with a higher water potential will ___________.",
A: "expand and then shrink",
B: "enlarge and become turgid",
C: "expand and then burst",
D: "decrease in size and become flaccid",
answer: "B. enlarge and become turgid",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Offspring formed by sexual reproduction exhibit more variation than those formed by asexual reproduction because _________.",
A: "greater amount of DNA is involved in sexual reproduction",
B: "gametes of parents have different genetic composition",
C: "genetic materials come from parents of two different species",
D: "sexual reproduction is a lengthy process",
answer: "B. gametes of parents have different genetic composition",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Radius and ulna are bones of the _________.",
A: "pectoral girdle",
B: "upper arm",
C: "pelvic girdle",
D: "lower arm",
answer: "D. lower arm",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. The blood vessel which carries blood from the alimentary canal to the liver is the ___________.",
A: "hepatic artery",
B: "hepatic vein",
C: "hepatic portal vein",
D: "mesenteric artery",
answer: "C. hepatic portal vein",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. Which of the labeled parts is the cortex?",
A: "I",
B: "II",
C: "III",
D: "IV",
answer: "D. IV",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. What is the main function of the organ?",
A: "Excretion",
B: "Respiration",
C: "Reproduction",
D: "Locomotion",
answer: "A. Excretion",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Detoxification of urea takes place in the ________.",
A: "pancreas",
B: "heart",
C: "liver",
D: "testes",
answer: "C. liver",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. Which of the following hormones is suddenly secreted into the bloodstream of a frightened person?",
A: "Insulin",
B: "Adrenaline",
C: "Thyroxine",
D: "Parathormone",
answer: "B. Adrenaline",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. The temperature control centre in mammals is located in the ________",
A: "skin",
B: "hypothalamus",
C: "pituitary gland",
D: "adrenal gland",
answer: "B. hypothalamus",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. The eye defect illustrated in the diagram is __________.",
A: "hypermetropia",
B: "astigmatism",
C: "presbyopia",
D: "myopia",
answer: "D. myopia",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The eye defect can be corrected by the use of _________.",
A: "convex lens",
B: "concave lens",
C: "bifocal lens",
D: "cylindrical lens",
answer: "B. concave lens",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. How many gametes are produced in the pollen grain of a flowering plant before fertilization?",
A: "One",
B: "Two",
C: "Three",
D: "Four",
answer: "B. Two",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Which of the following organisms does not undergo incomplete metamorphosis?",
A: "Locust",
B: "Grasshopper",
C: "Butterfly",
D: "Cockroach",
answer: "C. Butterfly",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. An enzyme reaction may begin to decline when _________.",
A: "the optimum temperature is attained",
B: "the pH of the medium is altered",
C: "grant",
D: "subscription",
answer: "A. the optimum temperature is attained",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. What precaution should have been taken to prevent the solution from turning green?",
A: "Use a non-green plant",
B: "Aerate the solution daily",
C: "Cover the culture vessel with opaque paper",
D: "Keep cotton wool around the seedling to make it dry",
answer: "C. Cover the culture vessel with opaque paper",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The death of the plant was likely caused by _________.",
A: "excess supply of nutrients to the plant",
B: "inadequate supply of water to the plant",
C: "algal growth in the solution that used up the nutrient",
D: "inability of the plant to make food due to lack of sunlight",
answer: "C. algal growth in the solution that used up the nutrient",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Which of the following factors is not necessary for photosynthesis?",
A: "water",
B: "Carbon (IV) oxide",
C: "Wind",
D: "Sunlight",
answer: "C. Wind",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Autotrophic nutrition is a process whereby an organism obtains food ___________.",
A: "by utilizing its stored energy",
B: "by synthesizing simple substances using energy",
C: "from other organisms in exchange for some products",
D: "in a synthesized form, from other living organisms",
answer: "B. by synthesizing simple substances using energy",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. The process that takes place at the light stage of photosynthesis is ___________.",
A: "splitting of water molecules to form hydrogen ions",
B: "reduction of carbon(IV) oxide to form carbohydrate",
C: "formation of two molecules of photoglyceric acid",
D: "breaking down of ATP molecules to produce energy",
answer: "A. splitting of water molecules to form hydrogen ions",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The adaptation of this type of foot is that it is ______________.",
A: "used as a bait to catch fish in water",
B: "used as a paddle for swimming",
C: "effective in scratching the soil for food",
D: "used for killing prey in water",
answer: "B. used as a paddle for swimming",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. The following organisms are examples of carnivorous plants except ___________.",
A: "Gloriosa",
B: "Venus flytrap",
C: "Pitcher plant",
D: "Utricularia",
answer: "A. Gloriosa",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Plants and animals of an ecosystem make up a _________.",
A: "habitat",
B: "succession",
C: "community",
D: "population",
answer: "C. community",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Rabbits cannot survive in an aquatic habitat because they have ___________.",
A: "no scales",
B: "no gills",
C: "fore limbs",
D: "lateral line",
answer: "B. no gills",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. What would happen if the population of domestic fowl decreases? The population of __________.",
A: "grasshoppers would decrease",
B: "hawks would increase",
C: "grasshoppers would increase",
D: "grasses available to grasshoppers would increase",
answer: "C. grasshoppers would increase",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Which of the following features is a characteristic of aquatic plants? Possession of __________.",
A: "multiple epidermis",
B: "heavily lignified tissue",
C: "finely divided leaves",
D: "succulent stem",
answer: "C. finely divided leaves",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. An association between living organisms in which one organism lives on and feeds at the expense of the other organism is known as _________.",
A: "mutualism",
B: "commensalism",
C: "parasitism",
D: "predation",
answer: "C. parasitism",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. When a large number of organisms share limited resources, the result is ____________.",
A: "mutualism",
B: "extinction",
C: "commensalism",
D: "competition",
answer: "D. competition",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. Which of the following behaviours is correctly matched with the corresponding diseases?",
A: "Smoking cigarettes",
B: "Having multiple sexual partners",
C: "Living near dirty gutters",
D: "Eating uncooked meat",
answer: "D. Eating uncooked meat",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Endangered species are organisms that are __________.",
A: "likely to migrate to other favourable lands",
B: "likely to disappear from the surface of the earth",
C: "reproducing profusely in an area",
D: "dangerous to humans and attacking other animals",
answer: "B. likely to disappear from the surface of the earth",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Which of the following practices is a wildlife conservation method?",
A: "Use of cover crops",
B: "Crop rotation",
C: "Mulching",
D: "Discourage poaching",
answer: "D. Discourage poaching",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Which of the following resources cannot be conserved?",
A: "Forest",
B: "Water",
C: "Soil",
D: "Garbage",
answer: "D. Garbage",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. The types of comb show ________.",
A: "variation",
B: "inheritance",
C: "cell theory",
D: "courtship behaviour",
answer: "A. variation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. Which factor is most likely responsible for the various types of comb?",
A: "Environment",
B: "Genetics",
C: "Physiology",
D: "Morphology",
answer: "A. Environment",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. Which of the following statements about mitosis is not correct?",
A: "Chiasmata are not formed",
B: "Bivalents are not formed",
C: "It does not lead to variation",
D: "Four daughter cells are produced",
answer: "D. Four daughter cells are produced",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. A mixture of blood with antigen A and blood containing antibody a will ____________.",
A: "lead to agglutination",
B: "facilitate dissolution of clot",
C: "have no effect on blood composition",
D: "change the blood group",
answer: "A. lead to agglutination",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. Plants suitable for experiments in genetics must not _______.",
A: "produce numerous seeds within a short time",
B: "have a small number of chromosomes",
C: "have a relatively short life cycle",
D: "produce one generation in a long period",
answer: "D. produce one generation in a long period",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Which of the following statements about sickle cell anaemia is correct?",
A: "It is caused by sex-linked genes",
B: "It is more common in males than in femaleS",
C: "Two sickle cell carrier parents may have a sickling chil",
D: "It is caused by a recessive gene",
answer: "D. It is caused by a recessive gene",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. In humans pointed eyebrows (B) is a dominant trait over smooth eyebrows (b). A student and the mother have smooth eyebrows while the father has pointed eyebrows. What is the genotype of the father?",
A: "BB",
B: "Bb",
C: "bb",
D: "BBbb",
answer: "B. Bb",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. A woman with Rhesus negative blood group was advised not to marry a man with Rhesus positive blood group because __________.",
A: "it will hinder her from having blood transfusion from her husband",
B: "it will result in sickness and probably death of the offspring",
C: "her children may all resemble her husband",
D: "it may affect her childbearing ability",
answer: "B. it will result in sickness and probably death of the offspring",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Which of the following organisms exhibits division of labour?",
A: "Butterfly",
B: "Cockroach",
C: "Termite",
D: "Housefly",
answer: "C. Termite",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. Natural selection arises as a result of _________.",
A: "gene mutation",
B: "change of habitat",
C: "reduction in population",
D: "climate change",
answer: "D. climate change",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. Which of the following statements is not Lamarck’s postulate on evolution?",
A: "Great changes in the environment result in corresponding changes in species",
B: "Frequently used organs become well developed while the ones not used become vestigial",
C: "Well developed acquired characters are inheritable",
D: "Survivors in a competitive community must have inherited useful trait",
answer: "D. Survivors in a competitive community must have inherited useful trait",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},


]